Today's דף daf is כ"ח, Kaf Chet, and we pick up at
the bottom of כ"ז עמוד ב', Kaf Zayin Amud Bet, and we
were actually looking at the question about the משנה Mishnah said you
can use anything for עירוב, Eruv, you can use anything for מעשר
שני Maaser Sheni with the exception of מעשר שני Maaser Sheni money
with the exception of water and salt, but then ר' יוחנן Reb
Yochanan of course said don't trust those types of global statements even
if it says except, and actually today is going to be a
lot of adding to the rule of except for. So we're starting
with מעשר שני Maaser Sheni and then we'll circle back to עירוב.
Eruv. The גמרא Gemara says that there's a debate whether according to
two תנאים, Tannaim, they were debating whether you could use fish brine
or not, they would both agree not salt water but they would
debate fish brine, but they both agreed fish were okay, and we
have others that are that say that fish would be no good
and the גמרא Gemara says the debate is here what type of
a דרשה drasha that you do. The פסוק pasuk says
ונתת הכסף בכל אשר תאוה נפשך בבקר ובצאן וביין ובשכר ובכל אשר
תשאלך נפשך, Venatata hakesef bechol asher te'aveh nafshecha babakar uvatzon uvayayin uvashichar
uv'chol asher tish'alcha nafshecha, you use money with anything your heart desires,
with cattle, sheep, wine, and meat, ובכל אשר תשאלך נפשך, uv'chol asher
tish'alcha nafshecha, anything your heart desires. General, narrow statement, more general statement.
So how do you what hermeneutics do you use to דרשן darshan
that? Do you use כלל ופרט וכלל, klal uprat uklal, which is
from the school of רבי ישמעאל, Rebbi Yishmael, for anybody that says
the sort of the pre פסוקי דזמרא Pesukei D'Zimra in the morning
רבי ישמעאל אומר בשלוש עשרה מדות, Rebbi Yishmael omer bishlosh esrei middot,
כלל ופרט וכלל, klal uprat uklal, or do you treat those exact
same statements but the way you categorize the rule is something called
ריבוי ומיעוט וריבוי, ribuy umi'ut uribuy, which is the רבי עקיבא Rebbi
Akiva school? And the basic difference is that ריבוי ומיעוט וריבוי ribuy
umi'ut uribuy leads to a broader category than כלל ופרט וכלל. klal
uprat uklal. כלל ופרט וכלל klal uprat uklal says after a כלל
klal and a פרט prat you have just the פרט, prat, so
the second כלל klal tells you anything like the פרט. prat. ריבוי
ומיעוט וריבוי ribuy umi'ut uribuy looks at the exact same words and
says once you have a ריבוי ribuy and a מיעוט, mi'ut, so
you know it couldn't just be the list, and then what's the
purpose of the ריבוי? ribuy? So already at stage two it says
anything like the list, so by stage three the next general statement
it says everything except things that are most dissimilar from the list.
So if that's your hermeneutics, then the only thing that's dissimilar from
the list are things like salt and water, things that aren't really
like minerals, you know, things that are not from the animal and
plant life. But if you do כלל ופרט וכלל, klal uprat uklal,
it has to be similar to the list. And what's similar to
the list? So let's just pick that up from the גמרא. Gemara.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: כלל ופרט וכלל, klal uprat
uklal, so I'm just going to read from five lines from the
bottom, אי אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט, ei ata dan ela k'ein
haprat, it has to be similar to the list, to the list,
so even at stage three it has to be it's only things
that are similar to the list. So what's similar? מה הפרט מפורש
פרי מפרי וגידולי קרקע, mah haprat meforash pri mipri vegidulei karka, the
same way the כלל klal is a fruit from fruit, again fruit
being used in the abstract, animals are fruits in the sense that
they're produced as opposed to like water and salt which aren't produced,
you know, they're just part of the mineral. Now what's פרי מפרי,
pri mipri, a fruit of a fruit? Why did they just say
a fruit? So רש"י Rashi in בבא קמא Bava Kamma says something
like a fruit of a fruit means like a wine. Wine is
not the original fruit itself, but it's produced from a fruit. So
we're not going to limit it to the sort of, you know,
to the stuff in their natural state. You can produce something from
them, but ultimately they are part they come from a פרי, pri,
something that is a fruit, וגידולי קרקע vegidulei karka and it grows
from the ground, אף כל פרי מפרי וגידולי קרקע. af kol pri
mipri vegidulei karka. So therefore it has to be anything like that.
Now what this excludes, we'll see, is basically like fish because although
they're פרי מפרי, pri mipri, they don't grow from the ground. And
we'll analyze that in a minute. I should say if you remember
yesterday
that תוספות, Tosafot, well okay we'll talk about that in a minute,
תוספות, Tosafot, you know, when the גמרא Gemara before mentioned an idea
of excluding you know, the גמרא Gemara had quoted a ברייתא braita
that said to exclude mushrooms, תוספות Tosafot said oh that was talking
about עירוב Eruv because they're not they need to be cooked, they're
not fit to be eaten, but actually the גר"א Gra there indicated
that no, that excludes from מעשר שני Maaser Sheni and רש"י Rashi
actually said that explicitly in בבא קמא Bava Kamma that פרי מפרי
וגידולי קרקע pri mipri vegidulei karka excludes mushrooms. א', Aleph, they're not
פרי מפרי, pri mipri, I mean they don't sort of come, a
mushroom doesn't come from like another mushroom, right? It comes from spores.
Well yes, but I guess it's not considered the same anyway. The
better answer is that it's not גידולי קרקע, gidulei karka, that although
they grow on things attached to the ground, they're really growing from
decomposing matter, they're not really growing from the nutrients of the ground.
And actually in the ברייתא braita of רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael of
the י"ג מדות שהתורה נדרשת בהן, Yud-Gimmel Middot shehaTorah nidreshet bahen, which
is a ברייתא braita that appears at the beginning of the ספרא
Sifra of the תורת כהנים, Torat Kohanim, it says what's an example
of כלל ופרט וכלל? klal uprat uklal? And the example it gives
is this case by מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, it says so it
has to be פרי מפרי וגידולי קרקע pri mipri vegidulei karka to
exclude mushrooms. So the ברייתא braita there explicitly uses this as the
paradigm of the principle of כלל ופרט וכלל klal uprat uklal and
excludes
mushrooms. So now the גמרא Gemara says, so it's a bigger list
of exclusions than just water and salt. So now the גמרא Gemara
says, ותניא אידך, ve-tanya idach, but we taught another ברייתא, Baraita, מה
הפרט מפורש ולד ולדות ארץ, mah ha-prat meforash vlad vladot aretz, a
descendant of the descendants of the land, אף כל ולד ולדות ארץ,
af kol vlad vladot aretz, even anything that's the descendant of the
descendants. That, by the way, is the language in the ברייתא Baraita
of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, not פרי מפרי, pri mi-pri, but the
ברייתא Baraita of י"ג מדות שהתורה נדרשת בהן, yud-gimmel middos she-ha-Torah nidreshet
ba-hen, the language is ולד ולדות ארץ. vlad vladot aretz. Now you
or I would have thought ולד ולדות vlad vladot and פרי מפרי
pri mi-pri is just two ways of saying the same thing, but
the גמרא Gemara thinks maybe there's a difference. So the גמרא Gemara
says מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? So according to both of these, it's
a more limited list. It has to be more similar
to the things in the תורה. Torah. But so what's the difference
if you articulate it as פרי מפרי pri mi-pri or ולד ולדות?
vlad vladot? So the גמרא Gemara says אמר אביי, amar Abaye, דגים
איכא בינייהו, dagim ika beinaihu, fish. למאן דאמר פרי מפרי וגידולי קרקע,
le-man de-amar pri mi-pri ve-gidulei karka, if you say food from fruit
and grows from the ground, הני דגים גידולי קרקע נינהו, hani dagim
gidulei karka ninhu, they grow from the ground. Now, as Michael pointed
out, even animals aren't גידולי קרקע, gidulei karka, and תוספות Tosafot points
this out a number of times. Sometimes the גמרא Gemara has a
narrow definition of גידולי קרקע, gidulei karka, which really means like plant
life, things that literally spring up from the ground, and sometimes it
means that things that get their nutrients from the ground, which even
is animal life that it eats off of the ground. So the
גמרא Gemara here is saying that if that's what גידולי קרקע gidulei
karka means, maybe fish are included, which is funny because they eat
other fish and they maybe get nutrients from vegetation that grows on
the water. But how many fish actually are bottom feeders and eat
things
that grow on the bottom?
I thought the thing was not גידולי קרקע gidulei karka by that
definition. Right. Well, I don't know. Where do ultimately fish, what are
fish eating other than other fish? Algae? Algae? Plants?
Yeah, but not the stuff that grows on the bottom of the
ground. So it's stuff that... no?
Well some do, like snails, they're not...
there are some bottom feeders...
but fish are the most amazing things... and they do really wild
things. Fish do it in a mass. Okay.
So anyway, that's... the גמרא's Gemara going to... the גמרא's Gemara going
to switch that. Whether here it's calling... it's willing to call them
גידולי קרקע. gidulei karka. Yes?
How does that differ from a carnivorous animal that never eats plant
life?
Yeah, but it eats other things that eat plant life. Here fish
don't... and it eats things that ultimately eat things that grow from
the ground. But if fish eat fish and those fish eat things
that grow... other fish and whatever... at some stage they eat plant,
but they eat plants that grow in the water, not plants that
grow on the ground. That would be the difference.
Yeah, carnivorous animals aren't כשר, kosher, so you couldn't buy מעשר שני
Maaser Sheni with them anyway, right?
Okay, well, that's a different story. But I mean, but in theory
would you buy... carnivorous birds. Right, there you go. Excellent point. Okay,
let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes with it. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says דגים איכא בינייהו. dagim ika beinaihu. So it's not...
הני דגים גידולי קרקע נינהו, hani dagim gidulei karka ninhu, they grow
off of the ground. למאן דאמר ולד ולדות הארץ, le-man de-amar vlad
vladot ha-aretz, those that say it descends from the land... now the
גמרא's Gemara assuming that ולד ולדות vlad vladot does not mean in
the current way it lives it gets from the ground, because then
it would be the same. It assumes that this is referring to
the way that they were created in the first פרק Perek of
בראשית. Bereishis. So דגים, dagim, so ולד ולדות vlad vladot means they
were created from the ground. Well we know
land animals were created from the ground, but fish, דגים ממיא איברו,
dagim mi-maya ivru,
they were created from the water. Okay. Problem also because
what else is created from the water? Right?
Salt?
Well we'll take a look.
What? Okay well anyway we'll take a look. So the גמרא Gemara
says what?
What is excluded from this פרי מפרי? pri mi-pri?
What is excluded? Well salt and, well salt we mentioned and water
and possibly... oh you mean why did you need פרי מפרי, pri
mi-pri, why couldn't you just say גידולי קרקע gidulei karka or ולד
ולדות הארץ? vlad vladot ha-aretz?
פרי מפרי Pri mi-pri includes fish, and it includes every organic material
I could think of... every animal, every plant...
obviously plants. Right. So you mean
why don't you just say גידולי קרקע? gidulei karka? Well, I think
because גידולי קרקע gidulei karka wouldn't have obviously excluded salt, because salt
is also coming from the ground. So if you're including פרי מפרי
pri mi-pri right, or it wouldn't necessarily have excluded... רש"י Rashi in
בבא קמא Bava Kamma says it's used to exclude salt and mushrooms.
Anyway, so let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says like this,
ומי אמר אביי דגים גידולי קרקע נינהו? u-mi amar Abaye dagim gidulei
karka ninhu? Would Abaye really put דגים dagim
under the גידולי קרקע gidulei karka category? ואמר אביי, ve-amar Abaye, אכל
פוטיטא, achal putita, a famous statement of אביי, Abaye, top of כח
ע"א, Kaf-Chet Amud Alef, if somebody eats פוטיטא, putita, which is some
type of a water insect, לוקה ארבע, lokeh arba, you get four
lashes because there are four different verbs that refer to not eating
insects, two of which are sort of generic, אל תשקצו את נפשותיכם
בכל השרץ השורץ, al teshaktzu et nafshoteichem be-khol ha-sheretz ha-shoretz,
רש"י Rashi says this three lines from the top, is one, ולא
תטמאו בהם, ve-lo titamu ba-hem, okay, so those are two generic prohibitions.
And then it says, two that are... כל אשר אין לו סנפיר
וקסקסת לא תאכלו kol asher ein lo snapir vekaskeset lo tocheilu and
מבשרם לא תאכלו. mibsaram lo tocheilu. So
anyway, you get four. You'll trust Abaye on the count. Okay, נמלה
nemala if you eat an ant, לוקה חמש, loke chamesh, you get
five lashes because the two generic and then three specific to insects
of the ground, of the earth. צרעה tzira if you eat like
a wasp, לוקה שש, loke shesh,
so it's two plus four. Okay, so anyway, what's the relevance of
all of this? So the גמרא Gemara says: ואי איתא, ve-i ita,
if it's true that fish are also considered to be of the
earth, of the land, so if they're גידולי קרקע gidulei karka for
the sense of מעשר שני, maaser sheni, they should also be that
for the sense of what type of an insect they are and
they should also be in the land insect category. פוטיתא נמי לוקי
משום שרץ השורץ על הארץ, putisa nami lukei mishum sheretz hashorait al
haaretz,
you should also get lashes for שרץ השורץ. sheretz hashorait. So don't
tell me דגים dagim are גידולי קרקע. gidulei karka.
Yeah, but the other verse specifically differentiates between water and the earth.
That's true.
What can I tell you? אלא אמר רבינא, ela amar ravina, so
says Ravina, let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes. עופות איכא בינייהו,
ofos ika beinaihu, the one that says it's עופות, ofos, למאן דאמר
פרי מפרי וגידולי קרקע, leman de-amar pri mipri vegidulei karka, if you
emphasize that they grow from the ground, currently they live off of
the ground, הני נמי גידולי קרקע נינהו, hanei nami gidulei karka ninhu,
birds live off the ground. למאן דאמר ולד ולדות הארץ, leman de-amar
vlad vladot haaretz,
if you say that they have to have been created from the
ground, הני עופות מן הרקק נבראו, hanei ofos min harakak nivreu, these
birds were created from the mud. What does that mean that they
were created from the mud? What, that's not ground? What? Well, what
does it mean that it was created from the mud? Does anybody
know? That's what
I was asking you, what wasn't created from, what also wasn't created
from the ground. I sort of you all a little dumbfounded, but
actually maybe because you were bothered by the difference between פרק א
perek alef and פרק ב perek bais of בראשית. bereishis. Because פרק
א perek alef is: ישרצו המים שרץ נפש חיה ועוף יעופף על
הארץ. yishretzu hamayim sheretz nefesh chaya ve-of ye-ofef al haaretz.
So your obvious answer should have been the other thing that wasn't
created from the ground was birds. The problem is that in פרק
ב perek bais of בראשית bereishis it says: ויצר ה' אלקים את
האדם עפר... vayitzer hashem elokim et ha-adam afar... no, not before the
אדם... adam... where is the פסוק? pasuk? ויצמח... vayatzmach...
well, where's the פסוק? pasuk? Yeah, ויצר ה' אלקים מן האדמה כל
חית השדה ואת כל עוף השמים ויבא אל האדם
לראות מה יקרא
לו. vayitzer hashem elokim min ha-adama kol chayat hasadeh ve-et kol of
hashamayim vayavei el
ha-adam
lirot mah yikra lo.
What do you mean
ואת כל עוף השמים? ve-et kol of hashamayim? He didn't... how could
you say ויצר מן האדמה? vayitzer min ha-adama? He was supposed to
have done it from the water. So the גמרא's Gemara resolution is
they were made from mud, a combination of water and dirt. Okay,
so anyway, so that's the גמרא's Gemara statement. Is that not ground
then? What? Apparently not. So that's the נפקא מינה. nafka mina. If
it has to be that what they were made from in the
story of מעשה בראשית, maaseh bereishis, birds would not be included. All
right, so that's the נפקא מינה. nafka mina. But everybody would exclude
fish. So if you have the דרשה drasha of, you know, that
it's everything except what's most dissimilar, the only thing you exclude is
water and salt. If you have it has to be like the
list, then certainly fish are not like the list and then the
question is if you, maybe also birds are not like the list
and that would be the issue about גידולי קרקע gidulei karka versus
ולד ולדות הארץ. vlad vladot haaretz. That's the כלל ופרט וכלל klal
u-prat u-klal approach, right, correct. So now, and certainly things like mushrooms
again are not like the list either because they're not גידולי קרקע
gidulei karka or because they're not considered פרי מפרי. pri mipri. Okay,
so they are fungi. So now the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, מאי...
mai... now the גמרא Gemara says like this: מאן דאמר בעופות מאי
טעמא ומאן דמיעט עופות מאי טעמא. man de-amar be-ofos mai taama u-man
de-miat ofos mai taama. So you've explained what's the difference of the
words פרי מפרי pri mipri versus ולד ולדות. vlad vladot. But at
the end of the day, we have this list: בבקר ובצאן וביין
ובשכר. babakar uvatzoan uvayayin uvashachar. One person says it only excludes fish
and the other one says it excludes fish and birds. Okay, why
would you take an approach to be more exclusive or less exclusive?
Where are you coming from, different approaches? 'Cause you're both agreeing to
the כלל ופרט וכלל klal u-prat u-klal approach. So why are you
going to be either more or less exclusive in terms of how
you sort of how you abstract the middle list, the פרט? prat?
You can say that's because one says...
No, that's descriptive. We understand that when you use that term, you
meant to exclude birds and when you use that term, you meant
to include birds. But why are you more exclusive and why are
you more inclusive if you're both agree to the כלל ופרט וכלל
klal u-prat u-klal
hermeneutics? Okay, so that's the גמרא's Gemara question. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: מאי... mai... so the גמרא Gemara says like this:
מאן דאמר בעופות מאי טעמא, man de-amar be-ofos mai taama, the one
who includes birds what's his reasoning? ומאן דמיעט עופות מאי טעמא, uman
de-miat ofos mai taama, and the one that excludes birds what's his
reasoning?
You're both abstracting from a list, why is one person more inclusive
than the other? So the גמרא Gemara says:
מאן דאמר בעופות קסבר כלל ו man de-amar be-ofos kasavar klal u
The one who's more inclusive, who includes birds, says you emphasize the
last כלל, פרט וכלל klal prat u'klal, נעשה כלל מוסיף על הפרט.
na'asah klal mosif al ha-prat. What this means is the following. Let
me make sure that I actually have a dry erase marker on
me. Okay. Is
here basically the way the sort of general hermeneutics works. If you
have a כלל ופרט, klal u-prat, okay, then we basically say all
that means is the פרט. prat. So if I say you can
use it for anything, you know, fish... I mean to say...
like בקר וצאן, bakar ve-tzon, like, you know, you can use it
for like cattle and sheep. If I were to tell you that,
you know, go ahead, get me anything for lunch, you know, like
a hamburger or a hot dog. So do I really mean anything?
No, I just mean the פרט. prat. So if you have כלל
ופרט, klal u-prat, we say you go by the פרט. prat. If
you have פרט וכלל, prat u-klal, if I say, yeah, you know,
go get me a hamburger or hot dog and get me anything.
So then it really means the כלל. klal, Okay? So if you
just had two, you say it means what the last thing you
said. If you have כלל ופרט וכלל, klal prat u-klal, then you
say, you know, get me anything for lunch, a hamburger, a hot
dog, anything. So then it's sort of like, okay, I sort of
mean anything like the middle. So it's כעין הפרט. ke-ein ha-prat. Okay.
So the question is how much do you interpret this? Do you
interpret this broadly, you know, as
quite broadly or not so broadly? So the גמרא Gemara says the
difference is going to be that you can look at a כלל
ופרט וכלל klal prat u-klal as a כלל ופרט klal u-prat plus
a כלל, klal. or you can look at it as a פרט
וכלל, prat u-klal, you know, plus, you know, plus, which of these
two building, which of these two does it build off of? If
you look at it first as a כלל ופרט, klal u-prat, then
you look at it as a narrow list, and then the extra
כלל klal, only broadens it so much. If you start by looking
at it as a פרט וכלל, prat u-klal, you look at it
as a big list. So then you're going to wind up at
the end with a bigger list because you started your first building
block was the פרט וכלל. prat u-klal. Okay, yes.
So for the first two, the כלל ופרט klal u-prat is just
the פרט, prat, and the פרט וכלל prat u-klal is just the
כלל. klal But you don't even have the first part of it.
Yeah, so that's the approach of, you know, ריבוי ומיעוט. ribuy u-miyut.
It's exactly because of that. I can't tell you, you know, I
couldn't tell you other than דיברה תורה כלשון בני אדם, dibra Torah
k'lishon bnei adam, which is sort of Rabbi Ishmael's approach anyway, so
maybe it fits in with that. Okay, so now let's take a
look at what the גמרא Gemara says, at how the גמרא Gemara
says. It says,
okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. So מאן דמרבי עופות,
man de-marbi ofos, if you're broader, קסבר כללא בתרא דוקא. kasavar klala
basra davka. You start by looking at the last כלל. klal. You
start by, your building block is the last two, the
פרט וכלל. prat u-klal.
So you start with
פרט וכלל. prat u-klal. Okay, so נעשה כלל klal. מוסיף על הפרט.
So if you just had that building block, you would say the
כלל klal adds to the פרט, prat, ואישתרבו לכל מילי, ve-ishrablu kol
milei, and you would have said everything was included. ואני כללא קמא,
va-hani klala kama, but to that building block you added the first
כלל, klal, and now it's transformed it into a כלל ופרט וכלל.
klal prat u-klal. So in the end, since you started with a
huge list, everything, you're even going to end with a pretty big
list because you started your first building block was the פרט וכלל.
prat u-klal. למיעוטי כל דלא דמי למשני צדדין, li-mutei kol de-lo dami
l'mishnei tzadin, and in the end, the only thing that that extra
כלל klal will do is exclude things that don't have two similar
characteristics. Right? The two similar is פרי מפרי וגידולי קרקע. pri mi-pri
ve-gidulei karka. Meaning at the end, your list will have be a
broader list, and it'll only be based on two characteristics. That's if
you start with the פרט וכלל prat u-klal at the end and
you start with everything.
Which is why you only exclude fish.
Which is why you'd only exclude fish and not birds. ומאן דממעיט
עופות, u-man de-mameit ofos, if you exclude birds, קסבר, kasavar, you're of
the opinion, כללא קמא דוקא. klala kama davka. You start with the,
your building block is the first כלל, klal, the first כלל ופרט.
klal u-prat. So the first כלל ופרט, klal u-prat, if that's your
first building block, that's only the פרט. prat. It's a very small
list. So דוקא כלל
ופרט. davka klal u-prat. So you start with כלל ופרט klal u-prat
as your building block. ואין בכלל אלא מה
שבפרט. ve-ein be-klal ela mah she-bi-prat. So the first part of that
three-part list, the first two tell you only the פרט. prat. It's
a very small list. הני אין מידי אחריני לא, hani in midiya
achrina lo, just these not other things. ואני כללא בתרא, va-hani klala
basra, so then the fact now it comes with the third component,
the last כלל, klal, לרבויי, le-rabuye, so that now broadens it. But
you're broadening something that starts as a very small list. So therefore
it has to be דמי ליה משלשה צדדין. dami lei mi-shlosha tzadin.
It has to have three characteristics that are similar, not just two.
So the three characteristics, the first two are פרי
מפרי pri mi-pri and גידולי קרקע, gidulei karka, excuse me, פרי מפרי
וגידולי קרקע. pri mi-pri ve-gidulei karka. And the third characteristic is not
only does it get its nutrients from the ground, but it's ולד
ולדות הארץ, vlad vladot ha-aretz, it was created from the ground. So
the basic point is is that even if you're in the כלל
ופרט וכלל klal prat u-klal category, sometimes we'll lose the thread, but
anyway, so even if you're in the כלל ופרט וכלל klal prat
u-klal category, which means it's going to wind up with anything similar
to the פרט. prat. You could still say how similar. How similar
in two ways, similar in three ways, there could still be a
debate about how broad that abstraction is going to be. And the
גמרא Gemara says the debate of how broad the abstraction is going
to be is as do you start by looking at the building
block as כלל פרט klal prat very narrow, so the
expansion will only be
moderately broad, or do you start by looking at it as a
פרט וכלל, prat u'klal, which is a complete list and therefore the
expansion also won't be everything, but it'll be pretty big. All right,
so that was an interesting גמרא Gemara about hermeneutics. Now back to
our discussion. The upshot of all of that was that even though
our משנה mishna says you can do anything with מעשר שני ma'aser
sheni except salt and water, in the end we see that there
are other things you can't do with it, especially if you're from
the school of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael and says כלל פרט וכלל,
you need it to be, you would exclude mushrooms and fish and
maybe even birds. Let's take a look.
חוץ מי chutz mi really means like mostly?
Well, that's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says. Don't trust those general
statements. Well, first of all, our תנא קמא Tanna Kamma might have
been the other school, might have been the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
school, which really the primary thing is that it would exclude would
be water and salt. So anyway, let's take a look now. אמר
רב יהודה משמיה דרבי שמואל בר שילת משמיה דרב. Amar Rav Yehuda
mishme d'Rabbi Shmuel bar Shilas mishme d'Rav. Now we get on back
to the first part of it, which is you can make an
עירוב eruv out of anything, again according to תוספות Tosafos we're just
talking about עירוב תחומין, eruv techumin, you can make an עירוב eruv
out of anything except salt and water. But now we're going to
really add to the list because the definition of עירוב eruv is
something that is normally edible. So the rest of today's דף daf
is going to be deciding what other things can you not make
an עירוב eruv out of? There's a lot of things other than
water and salt that are not really edible.
Like it could be like rancid meat?
Well, could be, yes, or even raw meat as we'll see. So
let's take a look. אמר רב יהודה משמיה דרב שמואל בר שילת
משמיה דרב מערבין בפפויין, Amar Rav Yehuda mishme d'Rav Shmuel bar Shilas
mishme d'Rav me'arvin b'papuin, you can make an עירוב eruv with, okay,
and here's where I'm going to need help here because I looked
up all these words, but again was translating a Hebrew word I
didn't understand with an English word I didn't understand. So Charlie, פפויין?
papuin? Cress. Cress. Okay. Artscroll says no one knows what
it is.
Well, Artscroll always says no one knows what it is, play it
safe. Okay, so
Sansino at least gives, not Sansino, Steinsaltz at least gives like a
best guess. Okay, so clearly all this is a best guess. ובחלגלוגות?
u'bechalgoogloit? Purslane. Purslane.
It's a common annual plant in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. There's a
picture of it. Okay, all right. ובגדגדניות? u'begud gadaniyot?
Sweet clover. Sweet clover. Coriander.
All right, whatever.
אבל לא בחזיז, aval lo bechaziz, not בחזיז, bechaziz, which is green
corn or green wheat, which is like the stuff that grows up
which you cut before it actually develops fully into a stalk of
wheat. ולא בכפניות u'lo bechafniyot and not with unripe dates. Those two
I know. ובגד... so okay, so you can't use those, those are
considered not fit for eating although they're some types of things that
grow from the ground and you might use some of it like
the חזיז chaziz, to feed the animals, these are not really considered
fit for human consumption and you cannot make an עירוב eruv out
of them. Presumably even if there are some people who do eat
it, it's not generally considered fit and cannot be used for an
עירוב. eruv.
Is this like actually a food or used as a spice? People
chewing down on coriander?
Well, I don't know. בכפניות bechafniyot are... oh... there's a note.
It says all three types are green vegetables which although commonly used
as spices are sometimes served as a meal. There you go. And
it's attributed to the ריטב"א. Ritba.
Okay, answered everybody.
Clover. Cows, right.
Okay
fine. I mean I guess if you have a salad, if you
can make a salad out of lettuce, why can't you make a
salad with clover, with shoots of clover? So anyway, all right, let's
take a look what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, okay. So now
the גמרא Gemara looks at this list. First about the things that
you can
use. ובגדגדניות מי מערבין? u'begud gadaniyot mi me'arvin? Can you really make
an עירוב eruv with
גדגדניות, gud gadaniyot, which we said was what? The third thing on
the list? Clover, that was the clover, sweet clover. Okay, can you
really do this? ותניא, ve'tanya, didn't we teach in a ברייתא, brayta,
גדגדניות מרבה בנים, gud gadaniyot marbe banim, מרבה בנים יאכלו. marbe banim
yochlu. If you have many kids, or מרובי בנים, merube banim, excuse
me, if you have many children then you should eat clover. Because
the גמרא Gemara basically believes that clover will cause sterilization in
men.
So therefore, okay, so it is true that obviously that surgical sterilization
is אסור דאורייתא. assur d'oraisa. More types of medicinal things that cause
sterilization is גרמא grama and whatever
issues around דרבנן d'rabanan and so on, but presumably you're not actually,
this is not like as directly causal, but it certainly can lead
to this medical issue. Okay, so it's like eating fatty things cause
high cholesterol and so on. It's not like a one to one
correspondence. It's not like you're doing an act of sterilization. All
right, yes, but anyway we won't get into the פרו ורבו peru
u'revu implications of this. Okay, but the point is here that this
clover, if somebody who has many kids, eat it. because, you know,
it'll maybe limit your amount of children you have. חשוכי בנים, chashuchei
banim, if you have, if you're, you know, barren of children, if
you don't have children, לא יאכלו, lo yochlu, don't eat it because
it'll make things worse. ואם הוקשו לזרע, ve-im hukshu le-zera, if the
plant became actually hardened and the seeds became hardened, so אף מרובי
בנים לא יאכלו, af merubei banim lo yochlu, then it's bad for
general health, and even people with a lot of kids shouldn't eat
it. So the גמרא Gemara says, so how can you say that
this is something to be eaten? The גמרא Gemara says, איבעית אימא,
iba'it eima, the גמרא Gemara says, תרגמא שלאו הוקשו לזרע מרובי בנים,
targama she-lo hukshu le-zera merubei banim, fine, we're talking about before the
plant has become hardened into seed, and we're talking about people that
are not so concerned that it might lead to sterilization. You could
also just talk about, okay, fine, so you know, men that were
anyway sterile, but maybe the גמרא Gemara felt that that wouldn't be,
you know, couldn't be proved absolutely anyway. Or women, right,
that's a good point. Actually that's an excellent point. What about women?
'Cause I don't think, 'cause at least the גמרא's Gemara talking in
the male and maybe it assumed it had a similar impact on
women, but as far as I know. No,
but that actually is an excellent point that if the גמרא's, Gemara
is the גמרא Gemara ignoring the entire past category of women here
that it's referring to? All right, anyway, yes, yes.
But this is going beyond is something edible or not to be
used for an עירוב, eruv, it's saying that certain people, certain people
can't eat it, like if you have a peanut allergy.
Right, but if everybody, if ninety percent of the population had peanut
allergies, then even though it's edible by ten percent, you would not
say that it's defined as food since ninety percent of people won't
eat it. Right? That's the גמרא's Gemara point. If it's broad, if
it's generally not eaten, right.
No, but they're defining it for the individual. If you have children.
Well, the גמרא's Gemara going to get to that issue in a
minute. Let's read the next line. Okay, but I think the גמרא's
Gemara general assumption was that in most cases people don't eat it.
Most people don't eat it most of the time. Okay, again, interesting
though that it is ignoring the possibility of women, unless it feels
either it's ignoring them or it thinks that the health concerns are
the same. Let's see the next answer of the גמרא, Gemara, which
is I believe getting to Rifka's point. The גמרא Gemara says like
this, ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'it eima, if you want I can say, לעולם
לחשוכי בנים, le-olam le-chashuchei banim,
even people that don't have kids can use this as an עירוב,
eruv, דחזו למרובי בנים. de-chazu le-merubei banim.
Right, because other people can eat it. It's, and even if they
can't, it can be eaten by other people. מי לא תנן, mi
lo tnan, did we not teach in our משנה? mishna? מערבין לנזיר
ביין ולישראל בתרומה, me'arvin le-nazir be-yayin u-le-Yisrael be-truma,
that a נזיר nazir can use wine and a ישראל Yisrael can
use תרומה. truma. So even though, אלמא אע"ג דלא חזי להאי חזי
להאי, alma af al gav de-lo chazi le-hai chazi le-hai, even if
the person using the food can't eat it, if it's fit for
other people, it's still considered food. הכא נמי אע"ג דלא חזי להאי,
hacha nami af al gav de-lo chazi le-hai, here too, even if
it's not fit for people who, you know, are concerned about the
sterilization effects, חזי להאי, chazi le-hai, it's fit for other people and
therefore it is still
food.
You could say that because there's so many foods that people are
allergic to or whatever that certain people can't eat.
Yes, but that's if it's a minority. I think the גמרא's Gemara
assuming here that if at, you know, that it could be a
majority, you know, fifty-fifty, or you know, at least roughly equal. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says, ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'it eima, if you want
you could say, כי קאמר רב, ki qamar Rav, when was רב
Rav talking that you could use it for an עירוב, eruv, because
it was רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in the name of רב שמואל
בר שילת Rav Shmuel bar Shilat in the name of רב, Rav,
בדקוקי מדאי, bi-dekuqi Madai,
so with the Median
sweet clover, which presumably is not a health concern for anyone. Okay,
so that's how he included clover on the list. Now on the
things that you can't do: ובחזיז לא, u-ve-chaziz lo, can you not
really use this חזיז, chaziz this like green corn, green wheat?
חזיז chaziz, is like hazizit almost, like it's green? Right? Is that
what that is? Is it the same like.
I don't know. והאמר רב יהודה אמר רב, ve-ha-amar Rav Yehuda amar
Rav, this also statement in the name of רב, Rav, so it's
the same רב Rav who says this, כשות וחזיז, kshuta ve-chaziz, if
you have כשות kshuta which is dodder.
Dodder?
What's
that? Hops? It is hops. It is hops.
It's basically hops. The description is basically hops. All right, there you
go. Hops and חזיז, chaziz, this like green wheat, מערבין בהן ומברכין
עליהן בורא פרי האדמה, me'arvin bahen u-mevarchin aleihen borei pri ha-adama, you
can use for an עירוב eruv and you make a בורא פרי
האדמה borei pri ha-adama because they grow from the ground and they're
fit for eating. I mean, and therefore you make the ברכה bracha
בורא פרי
האדמה.
borei
pri ha-adama.
If you eat them raw.
If you eat them raw, yeah, or whatever, cooked in a way
they haven't completely transformed them. So anyway you see that it's, you
can make an עירוב, eruv, how could he say you can't? The
גמרא Gemara says, לא קשיא, lo qashya, it's not difficult. הא מקמי
דאתא רב לבבל הא לבתר דאתא רב לבבל. ha mikamei de-ata Rav
le-Bavel ha le-vatar de-ata Rav le-Bavel. When he said you couldn't was
when he was living in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, and in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael nobody ate them, so he assumed they weren't treated
as food. They were treated as animal food; they weren't treated as
human food. When he came to בבל, Bavel, he saw that people
ate it, so he revised his position. But is בבל Bavel even.
Ah, so that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to say. The גמרא
Gemara says, ובבל הויא רובא דעלמא, u-Vavel havya ruba de-alma, is בבל
Bavel the majority of the world? Why should בבל Bavel determine? Now
this is quite fascinating because we just got through saying if it
worked for some, it worked for all. So let's read the גמרא
Gemara and then go back to that. והא. ve-ha. והתניא, Ve'hatanya, I'll
prove to you that even if certain people want to eat something,
you go by the more universal definition. So and the proof is
not going to be from an עירוב Eruv question, but from a
different
issue: הפול והשעורה והתילסון. Hapul ve'ha'se'ora ve'ha'tilson. So if you have פול
pul which are beans, שעורה se'ora barley, תילסון tilson is fenugreek. Oh
my gosh, I got that one right. Okay, now, apparently those things
are basically planted for their seeds. But שזרען לירק, she'zaran le'yerek, if
you planted them for to use them as their vegetables, like for
their leaves and to eat them, you know, not for their seeds,
so בטלה דעתו אצל כל אדם. batla da'ato etzel kol adam. Then
you know what you're intending has no relevance because it's not what
normal people do. And what's the halakhic implications? לפיכך זרען חייב וירקן
פטור. Lefikach zaran chayav ve'yarkan patur. It's a מעשר ma'aser question. So
their seeds, you might say, well look, I planted them for to
treat them as a vegetable and eat the stalks, so I should
only take מעשר ma'aser off the stalks and not the seeds. No,
what you wanted to do was seen as totally weird and therefore
there's still the defined that the basic food part of this plant,
whatever you were intending, is still the seeds. So only the seeds
are חייב chayav in מעשר ma'aser and not the vegetable
part. והשחליים והגרגיר. Ve'hashachalayim ve'hagargir. Now, when it comes to שחליים shachalayim
and גרגיר, gargir, which are, Charlie?
Cress and arugula.
And what? Argula? Arugula. Okay. It's also known as garden rocket. The
second one?
Yeah, rocket or arugula is... Ah, it's a variety of rocket.
Oh, okay. All right,
cress and arugula, of which one variety is garden rocket. Since those
things can be eaten both for their sort of, you know, stalks
and as a vegetable and also for their seeds, so there your
intention matters. שזרען לירק, She'zaran le'yerek, if you planted them to treat
it as a vegetable, מתעשרין ירק וזרע, mitasrin yerek va'zera, you take
מעשר ma'aser off of both, but the ירק yerek part is the
dominant definition. So what does that mean? It's dominant, it also says,
you know, there's different questions which year of the שמיטה shmita cycle
something is in. And for things that are vegetables, it's defined by
the year that it was harvested. By things that are more like
grains that you do for their seeds, it goes more about the
time when they were developed, even before they were harvested. So here
it's primarily, and other implications as well. So because you intended as
a vegetable, its primary definition is as a vegetable, but the seeds
also require מעשר ma'aser because people eat the seeds. זרען לזרע, Zaran
le'zera, and if you did it for their seeds, מתעשרין זרע וירק.
mitasrin zera ve'yerek. Then also you take both מעשרות, ma'asrot, but its
primary definition is זרע. zera. Anyway, the point of all of this
is that even if you plan on eating something, if it's considered
totally bizarre, we ignore. So who cares that בבל Bavel eats חזיז,
chaziz that should be considered insignificant. Now, it's quite interesting. What about
the point before, right, where the גמרא Gemara spoke about this thing
which was a health product and it still said as long as
it's fit for some people? And I think that the difference here,
and I think maybe this is the point that Rifka was making,
is is that when it is, you know, in terms of when
it's seen as sort of food for humans, you know, fit for
human consumption, then if there's some secondary reason you're not eating it,
it's תרומה terumah and I'm a ישראל, Yisrael, it's wine and I'm
a נזיר, nazir, there are health concerns. All of those are like
secondary, then we say as long as it's fit for somebody because
its basic definition is food. But if something's basic definition is animal
food and not human food, so if you find a few people
that eat it, בטלה דעתו. batla da'ato. Now, the תוספות Tosafot says,
but בבל Bavel is not a few people. בבל Bavel is like
a whole country! So תוספות Tosafot discusses when do we consider that
to change the definition. I would agree with you, you know, that
intuitively, if a whole country eats it, certainly if you're in בבל,
Bavel, that should count. Okay, it is interesting that... So yeah, this
sounds like it's not the case, but then again it's pretty funny.
How could you say בטלה דעתו אצל כל אדם batla da'ato etzel
kol adam if you're in בבל? Bavel?
Yeah. There's a case in point: the locusts in ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. Although many of the, particularly Western
people, are repulsed by
them, lots of people eat them and they're kosher. Right.
Well, you have to have a מסורה, masorah, but if you have
the מסורה masorah about what kind, the issue with the locust is
you need that, you know, only if you have the מסורה masorah
about what's in the category of the תורה Torah that the תורה
Torah has identified. But yeah, but I mean it is true that,
you know, there are things that some people would think is repulsive
and other people treat as normal food.
More interestingly, it's kosher for me and it's not kosher for you.
Well, yeah, I mean
that's true, some people don't eat turkey. Okay, anyway, so but anyway
it is interesting. Maybe the גמרא Gemara is saying outside of בבל
Bavel it wouldn't count, maybe inside of בבל Bavel it would. Anyway,
interestingly here that if something is considered to be animal food by
the majority of the world,
even if in בבל Bavel not, that's not going to make a
difference.
These questions are particularly relevant to the עירוב חצירות Eruv Chatzerot because
we're talking about a group of people.
Oh, that's interesting.
So in a group they have different tastes or medical...
Right, but the עירוב חצירות... Eruv Chatzerot... תוספות Tosfos points out that
the גמרא Gemara later is going to make it very clear that
עירוב חצרות Eiruv Chatzeiros was only bread. So עירוב Eiruv here means
the עירוב תחומין. Eiruv Techumim. But you are right that the end
of the משנה Mishnah also does apply to שיתופי מבואות, shitufai mevo'os,
so also there's an issue about the collective and does it have
to be fit for everybody that's of that collective. Okay, but here
the גמרא Gemara even says look even if for an individual not,
but again that was when it was a secondary concern. Here in
the basic definition of is it human food, it needs to be
more universal. So the גמרא Gemara says, so let's see what the
גמרא's Gemara answer is. כי אמר רב, Ki amar Rav, when did
רב Rav say that this חזיז chaziz is considered to be is
is
considered to be one minute...
so the problem is is that רב Rav had said that by
חזיז chaziz in one place he said you can't use it, and
another place he said you could. So the גמרא Gemara says, when
he said you could was after he came to בבל. Bavel. But
the גמרא's Gemara saying that shouldn't make a difference because in most
places it's not human food, so כי אמר רב, Ki amar Rav,
when did רב Rav say in his second statement that you can
use it, that it is considered to be food?
בדגונייסא, Bedigunaisa, if it's garden the garden variety of חזיז chaziz which
apparently everybody eats and therefore it is considered food. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara says now the גמרא Gemara analyzes stops you know the
עירוב eiruv discussion for a minute and goes back to that ברייתא
brayisa that talked about whether you were planting certain things for their
vegetable you know for their stalks or for their seeds. So the
גמרא Gemara says,
גרגיר למאי חזי, gargir lemai chazi, what do you use arugula for,
זרע גרגיר, zera gargir, what would what do you use the seeds
of arugula for? Because the גמרא Gemara says the ברייתא brayisa said
if you planted it for the seeds then it's considered the seeds
are significant for מעשר ma'aser purposes. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר
רבי יוחנן שכן ראשונים שלא היה להן פלפלין Amar Rabbi Yochanan, shekein
rishonim shelo haya lahen pilpilin because the early generations, interesting, early generations,
I mean but anyway that did not have pepper, שוחקים אותן
ומטבילים בהן את הצלי shochakim osan umatbilin bahen es hatzali they ground
it up and they dipped the roast meat into it. They used
this as a pepper substitute. Apparently according to Steinsaltz in many places
in the world where they didn't have pepper they used arugula as
a pepper substitute. But it's interesting here that they that he makes
it chronological, ראשונים, rishonim, earlier generations. Anyway, that's why that is considered
significant if you want it for the seeds.
So I have a question. Yes. So like you know I remember
earlier then you know remember it was like this כותח הבבלי kutach
habavli we talked about and the people in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
like hated that stuff. Right? So the people in ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael then wouldn't be able to use it right?
Yeah again I don't know because the whole idea that בבל Bavel
counts as an it doesn't count as a significant place is is
bizarre. So I don't really know how to answer that.
And the other way around like there was like something that the
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael the Babylonians... right so like you know yeah
it's hard to imagine why you shouldn't define the food that's good
for an entire large geographic area at least for the people of
that area. Okay let's take a look as the גמרא Gemara continues.
רבי זירא כי הוה חשיש מגרסיה Rabbi Zeira ki hava chashish migirsei
when רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira was getting tired used to get tired
from his learning like you know he needed to take you know
he needed like a little בטלה. batala. So what would he do
for his בטלה batala when he needed a little break from his
learning? הוה אזיל Hava azil he would talk sports. No. הוה אזיל
ויתיב אפתחא דרב יהודה בר אמי Hava azil veyasiv apat-cha deRav Yehuda
bar Ami he would go and he would sit by the doorway
of רב יהודה בר אמי Rav Yehuda bar Ami and he said,
כי נפקי ועייילי רבנן, ki nafki ve'ayili rabbanan, when the רבנן rabbanan
go in and out of the בית מדרש, beis medrash, איקום מקמייהו
ekum mikamayihu I'll get up for you know in front of you
know in their presence when they walk in front of me, ואקבל
בה אגרא ve'akabel bo agra and I'll get שכר s'char for showing
כבוד kavod to a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham which is quite fascinating
because he is obviously a senior rabbi. And the רבנן rabbanan when
we speak about the rabbis of the house of whatever we mean
like the rabbinic students. So but still so showing they'd be standing
for him but this is what he did in order to get
שכר s'char even if he couldn't focus on his learning. Okay, so
נפק אתא ינוקא דבי רב, nafka asa yanuka debei rav, so you
know
came out a school child not even a you know
not even a ישיבה בחור, yeshiva bachur, school child came out. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, so obviously even when he wasn't learning he had
to be learning, so he said מאי אגמרך רבך, mai agmarach rabach,
what did your רבי Rebbe teach you? אמר ליה Amar lei so
he said to him כשות kashus when it comes to כשות kashus
which are hops, right, yes, okay got that right, בורא פרי האדמה.
borei pri hadama. חזיז chaziz when it comes to this green weed,
שהכל נהיה בדברו shehakol nihiyeh bidvaro which by the way fits because
we said the חזיז you cannot use for an עירוב, eiruv, which
is meaning it's not really considered fit for eating. So even if
you eat it you would only say a שהכל, shehakol, whereas the
כשות kashus we said was fit for an עירוב, eiruv, so right
was the כשות kashus on the list of what was, yeah כשות
וחזיז kashus v'chaziz bar-bar... okay so that's consistent with what we've been
talking about. אמר
ליה Amar lei so he said to him אדרבה איפכא מסתברא adaraba
ip-cha mistabra what do you mean the opposite makes more sense. האי
מארעא קמרבי, Hai me'ara kamirbi,
the green grain grows from the ground and therefore it should be
בורא פרי האדמה, borei pri hadama, ignoring the fact that it's not
really ripe yet and not fully fit for eating. And the high
and the hops מאווירא קמרבי Me'avira kamarbei grow from the air which
apparently according to Soncino means that it's a parasitic plant and actually
gets its nutrients not straight from the ground but by sucking it
out of the plant that it's intertwined with. Okay so so that
is less of a בורא פרי האדמה, Borei pri ha'adama, that's more
of a שהכל. Shehakol. So the גמרא Gemara says והלכתא כינוקא דבי
רב, Ve'hilchata k'yenuka d'bei Rav, but we rule like the schoolchild. It's
funny right because we don't know who he said in the name
of, he said what did your rebbe teach you? Could have said
so, could have said you know he was sitting by the doorway
of you know of רב יהודה בר אמי, Rav Yehuda bar Ami,
but maybe since he wasn't explicitly attributed as the rebbe, so it's
sort of a fascinating thing. We פסקן pasken like the schoolchild and
not like רבי זירא. Rabbi Zeira. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, so he
sat by the, I know,
what's the reason? האי גמר פירא Hai gmar peira because hops are
a completed fruit and therefore it gets a בורא פרי האדמה Borei
pri ha'adama and האי, ve'hai, the green grain, לאו גמר פירא lav
gmar peira is not completed and as we saw before not only
is it not ripe but it's not even considered food for them
at this stage. Maybe it's only animal food. ומה דקאמרת האי מארעא
קא רבי והאי מאווירא קא רבי, Uma d'ka'amart hai me'ara ka rabei
ve'hai me'avira ka rabei, the point that you were saying that this
one is ground and this one is air, meaning specifically on the
hops, even if the hops are fully ripened how do you make
a בורא פרי האדמה? Borei pri ha'adama? The גמרא Gemara says לא
היא כשותא נמי מארעא קא רבי. Lo hi keshuta nami me'ara ka
rabei. It's not true, the כשותא keshuta also grows from the ground
indirectly. דהא קחזינן, De'ha kachazinan, we see דקטלינן ליה להיזמא de'katlinan lei
l'hizma when you cut down the bush, like the thorn bush that
it's growing off of, ומיית כשותא, umayeit keshuta, the כשותא keshuta dies,
the hops die. So they are actually getting nutrients from the host
plant and that's enough to call them בורא פרי האדמה, Borei pri
ha'adama, to call them growing from the ground. I assume that's different
than mushrooms,
right? If you took I don't know where mushrooms get it from
like dying decaying matter, right?
They directly absorb nutrients
from the ground without like a vascular without roots and so on
and they don't do photosynthesis, they don't make anything they just consume.
But do they get the same nutrients from the ground that plants
do?
It depends on where they're growing. They could grow on a decaying
tree or they could grow in the ground and in the latter
case they would get it from.
But if they're growing on a decaying tree it could grow on
a dead decaying tree, right? Okay so that's how it's different that
it actually is possible for mushrooms to grow off on things that
are not attached from the ground. But hops is not possible so
it gets a בורא פרי האדמה. Borei pri ha'adama. Okay so now
the גמרא Gemara says like
this, okay. ובכפנייתא אין מערבין, U'vechafniata ein me'arvin, can you not make
an ערוב eruv with כפנייתא chafniata which are unripe dates? So again
it gets to the unripe issue and therefore not fully fit to
be eaten. והתניא, Ve'hatanya, didn't we teach in a ברייתא braita קור
kor which is heart of palm, ניקח בכסף מעשר, nikach b'chesef ma'aser,
you can use מעשר ma'aser money for it, it's פרי מפרי וגידולי
קרקע pri mipri v'gidulei karka right and ואינו מטמא טומאת אוכלין. ve'eino
mitamei tumat ochlin. Interestingly
you can use it for מעשר ma'aser money but it does not
become to have the impurity of foodstuff because it's considered to be
like the actual like the trunk of a tree, it's considered to
be wood. So it's wood that is a פרי מפרי pri mipri
right and grows from the ground and it is edible okay but
because it's identified with the trunk, yeah
why?
Because it's a stem.
Yeah but you know that's sort of like a vegetable. This is
part of something that's a tree. So because it's part of the
trunk of a tree it's considered to be wood and not food.
It's so bizarre though because that's what's again like once people eat
it doesn't that transfer definition into food? So okay let's see about
that. וכפנייתא, Ve'chafniata, now but the unripe dates ניקחות בכסף מעשר nikachot
b'chesef ma'aser you can use מעשר ma'aser money, again פרי מפרי וגידולי
קרקע pri mipri v'gidulei karka ומטמאות טומאת אוכלין u'mitama'ot tumat ochlin and
those are considered to be food because those are you know come
off of the tree, they're not the tree itself. רבי יהודה אומר,
Rabbi Yehuda omer, now רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says קור הרי הוא
כעץ לכל דבריו, kor harei hu k'etz l'chol devarav, קור kor is
like a the heart of palm is like the tree is like
a tree, אלא שניקח בכסף מעשר ela shenikach b'chesef ma'aser
but you can use but buy it with מעשר ma'aser which seems
to be the exact same as the first statement which said you
could buy it with מעשר ma'aser but it's not considered food. We'll
get back to that. וכפנייתא Ve'chafniata now the unripe dates הרי הן
כפרי לכל דבריהם, harei hen k'pri l'chol divreihem, those are fully a
fruit, אלא שפטורות מן המעשר, ela she'peturot min ha'ma'aser, you don't take
מעשר ma'aser off of them because they're not fully a fruit but
anyway hold on just want to check רש״י Rashi on this right
because because they are not fully ripe. So you don't take מעשר
ma'aser off of them.
So that's different.
Because they're not subject to מעשר ma'aser yet. Right
right. So so the first part sounds the same as the תנא
קמא tanna kamma but in terms of these unripe dates the תנא
קמא tanna kamma says that they are
מטמאות טומאת אוכלין, mitama'ot tumat ochlin, wait a minute right, תנא קמא
Tanna kamma didn't exclude them from anything. So according to the תנא
קמא tanna kamma they presumably even these unripe dates would be חייב
chayav in מעשר ma'aser but according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda the
one thing he says is that they're not חייב chayav in מעשר,
ma'aser, they're not totally ripened. So how much are they considered is
debated. But what you see is that both of them hold that
they're considered to be, you can use it with מעשר maaser, *ma'aser*
money, they're מטמא טומאת אוכלין tum'at ochlin, *metame tumas ochlin*, so they're
a food, they're פרי מפרי *pri mipri*. So how could we say
that you can't use them for עירוב eiruv, *eiruv* purposes? So that's
the question. So whether or not you take מעשר maaser, *ma'aser* we'll
get to, but the first focus of the question is how can
you say you cannot use these unripe dates? And here the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* makes an important introduction into what's required
for, well first, and it's going to get to a new criteria
for עירוב eiruv *eiruv* which I mentioned yesterday, עירוב *eiruv* food. So
first the גמרא'ס *Gemara's* answer is the following: בניסחני *benis'chani*. No. When
are we saying in this ברייתא braita, *braisa* that they're considered you
can use מעשר maaser *ma'aser* money and they're food? That's with a
type of unripe dates that never
ripen. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says that's from the male palm as opposed
to the female palm, actually palm trees are gendered. So that's the
type that never ripens. So a type that never ripens, that's when
everybody agrees it's food because then you would eat it in that
stage. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: one minute. אי הכי *ei
hachi*, if it's the type that never ripens, והא לימא רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda פטור מן המעשר *v'ha leima Rabbi Yehuda patur min hama'aser*,
how could he say it's exempt from מעשר maaser *ma'aser*? I mean,
if it never gets beyond a certain stage of development, then it's
as developed as it's going to get if that's the type of
date you're talking about. So why would he exempt it from מעשר
*ma'aser*? And not only logically would it not make sense, we have
proof that he does it. דתניא *de-tanya*, taught in the ברייתא *braisa*:
אמר רבי יהודה *amar Rabbi Yehuda*, says Rabbi Yehuda, the same Rabbi
Yehuda: הותרו פגי בית סייני *hutru pagei Baisayoni*.
So in a certain discussion in you know, where there was about
שביעית *Shevi'is*, it mentioned these unripe figs of בית סייני *Baisayoni* and
he says that's not relevant for that discussion, the only relevant for
this unripe figs of בית סייני *Baisayoni* is לעניין מעשר בלבד *l'inyan
ma'aser bilvad*, is for מעשר *ma'aser* purposes. And what does that mean?
פגי בית סייני *pagei Baisayoni*, these unripe figs, והציני דטובינא *v'hatzini d'Tuvina*,
and the unripe dates of טובינא *Tuvina*, חייבין במעשר *chayavin
b'ma'aser*. Those are obligated in מעשר *ma'aser*. So anyway, the important part
for us is he says these unripe dates that come from the
male palm tree that never get fully ripe are חייב chayav, *chayav*
in מעשר *ma'aser*. So again, the גמרא'ס *Gemara's* question is: how can
you say unripe... let me pull back and tell you what we're
saying. The first statement was unripe dates you can't use for עירוב
*eiruv* purposes. Okay, but we have a ברייתא *braisa* that says that
everybody agrees that unripe dates you can buy מעשר *ma'aser*... use for
מעשר *ma'aser* money, מטמא טומאת אוכלין tum'at ochlin *metame tumas ochlin*, so
presumably it's food. So the גמרא'ס *Gemara's* first answer is that was
talking about the male variety which never get ripe and they're different.
The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* rejects that because if it was the male
variety nobody would ever exclude it from anything. So we're back to
saying they're all talking about the female variety. So if that's true,
how could you say you can't use it for מעשר *ma'aser* if
in the ברייתא *braisa* everybody says it's considered food? So here's the
גמרא'ס *Gemara's* important answer. The גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says like this: אלא עולם לאו בניסחני *ela olam lav benis'chani*.
We're not talking about the male types. And nevertheless, there's a difference.
לעניין טומאת אוכלין tum'at ochlin *l'inyan tumas ochlin*, when it comes to
like the idea, can you use מעשר *ma'aser* money for it or
is it considered food for the טומאה tumah *tumah* of food stuffs,
שאני *shani*, there it's different. Why? כי אמר רבי יוחנן amar Rabbi
Yochanan, *ki amar Rabbi Yochanan*, like Rabbi Yochanan says: הואיל וראוי למתקן
על ידי האור ho'il v'ra'uy l'matkan al yedei ha'ur, *ho'il v'ra'uy l'matkan
al yedei ha'or*,
you can sweeten them by cooking them. הכא נמי הואיל וראוי למתקן
על ידי האור *hacha nami ho'il v'ra'uy l'matkan al yedei ha'or*. Here
too, you can sweeten them by cooking them. Which means, okay, this
is a point that I told you yesterday. עירוב *eiruv* has to
be fit to be eaten in the state it is right now.
Okay, but you can for example use your מעשר *ma'aser* money to
buy raw meat. You can't make an עירוב *eiruv* with raw meat.
Okay, so similarly,
some type of a thing that can be easily made edible by
putting it on a fire is considered enough of a food for
טומאת אוכלין tum'at ochlin *tumas ochlin* and obviously enough of a food
for your מעשר *ma'aser* money, but it wouldn't work for עירוב *eiruv*
which has to be fit to be eaten in the state it
is right now. Okay, so that's the difference here which is just
that it's not prepared enough to be fit for an עירוב *eiruv*,
but if you prepared it, that would be a different story. So
היכא דאיתמר D'itmar, דרבי יוחנן *heicha d'itmar d'Rabbi Yochanan*, where was the
original statement of Rabbi Yochanan that if you can sweeten it by
the fire, you know, by cooking it, it makes a difference? אהא
דתניא *aha d'tanya*, what we taught in the ברייתא *braisa*: שקדים המרים
*shkedim hamarim*, if you have these bitter almonds, קטנים חייבים גדולים פטורים
*ktanim chayavim
gdolim pturim*. When they're small, they're obligated because when they're small, it's
a species of almonds. So when they're small, they still don't taste
bitter, so they're edible. So then they're חייב chayav *chayav* in מעשר
*ma'aser*.
So what's the שקדים המרים *shkedim hamarim*?
It's a certain type of almonds. No, they're bitter almonds. Like you
know, like crab apples. Okay, it's a type. So those things though
are still edible before they fully ripen. So when they are unripe,
they're חייב chayav, *chayav* in מעשר *ma'aser* because they're edible. גדולים *gdolim*,
if they ripen, פטורים *pturim*, then they're exempt because they're inedible. מתוקים
*metukim*, if it is sweet almonds, then it's the opposite. גדולים חייבים
*gdolim chayavim*, when they're ripened, they're obligated because they're edible. קטנים *ktanim*,
when they're still small, then they're bitter and they're inedible, פטורים *pturim*,
they're exempt from מעשר *ma'aser*. ואמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *v'amar Rabbi
Yochanan* יוסי אומר משום אביו, רבי שמעון ברבי יוסי Rabbi Shimon barbi
Yossi said in the name of his father, רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi,
זה וזה לפטור, zeh v'zeh liftur, which רש"י Rashi, says means the
bitter type are both exempt. When they're small, they're exempt because they're
unripe. When they're big, they're exempt because they're inedible. ואמרי לה זה
וזה לחיוב, V'amreilah zeh v'zeh l'chayev, and
some say that they're both חייב, chayav? that when they're small, even
though they're unripe they're edible, and when they're big, they're חייב chayav
because they're ripe even though they're not so fully edible. Anyway, so
אמר רבי אילא, amar Rabbi Ila, הא רבי חנינא בציפורי כדברי האומר
זה וזה לפטור. ha Rabbi Chanina b'Tzipori k'divrei ha'omer zeh v'zeh liftur.
Rabbi Chanina ruled in ציפורי Tzipori that the bitter variety are always
exempt, either because they're unripe or because they're inedible. And now the
גמרא Gemara says, ומאן דאמר זה וזה לחיוב למאי חזי? Uman de'amar
zeh v'zeh l'chayev lemai chazi? But if you say the bitter variety
is always חייב, when it's small because it's sweet, what's when it's
big? Why would that be חייב? It's inedible, it's bitter! So here's
where רבי יוחנן says, אמר רבי יוחנן, הואיל וראוי למתקן על ידי
האור,
because you can sweeten them by cooking them. So when it comes
to other questions of טומאת אוכלין, מעשר, is it חייב in מעשר,
do you use מעשר שני maaser sheni money for it, there the
idea that maybe it needs to be cooked a little to be
made edible makes a difference. But when it comes to עירוב, that
has to be fit to be eaten in exactly the state it
is right now. Okay, so now we've dealt with all the statements
of things that we've added to the list of things that you
can't make an עירוב for. And now we have to get back
to this statement we made before about the heart of palm. So,
אמר מר, amar Mar, we said before, רבי יהודה אומר קור הרי
הוא כעץ לכל דברו. Rabbi Yehuda omer kore harei hu k'etz l'chol
devaro. The heart of palm is like wood in all respects. אלא
שניקח בכסף מעשר, Ella shenikach b'kesef maaser, but because you can use
מעשר money for it, because it's edible although it's wood. So the
גמרא says, היינו תנא קמא? hainu tanna kamma? That's like the first
opinion which basically said you can use מעשר for it but it's
not considered אוכל ochel because for טומאת אוכלין purposes. So אמר אביי,
amar Abaye, שלקא ותגנא איכא בינייהו. shulka v'tigna ika beinaihu.
If you sort of like boiled it and fried it, what would
that be? That would be a difference. Because if you boiled it
and fried it, so if you take a look at רש"י, Rashi
I just want to show you, רש"י Rashi, says דתגנא, בשמן, detigna
b'shemen, see the next word in רש"י, about 20 lines from the
bottom, דתגנא detigna, בשמן, b'shemen, fried, or frit, isn't that fritters? Fritters,
fried? Okay, so anyway, I'm guessing the same word. So the גמרא
says that when you say that it's wood, then you're totally categorically
excluding it. So even if you fried it and made it much
more edible, you would still exclude it. It'd be fried wood. But
according to the תנא קמא, tanna kamma, maybe if you fried it,
it would be considered to be food. So the גמרא says, מתקיף
לה רבא, maskif lah Rava, so Rava asked them this, מי איכא
למאן דאמר שלקא ותגנא לא? mi ika leman de'amar shulka v'tigna lo?
Would anybody say that if you boiled and fried it, no? That
if you really do things that make it really edible, everybody agrees
it is food for טומאה for טומאת אוכלין purposes. והתניא, V'hatanya, we
taught in a ברייתא, העור והשליא, ha'or v'hashilya, if you have leather,
the skin of an animal, the hide I should say, or a
placenta, אין מטמאין טומאת אוכלין, ein mitam'in tum'at ochlin, those are not
considered to be food. עור ששלקו, Or sheshelako, but if you if
you boiled it, והשליא שחישב עליה, v'hashilya shechishev aleha, or if you
planned to eat the placenta, apparently the placenta is more immediately edible
but normal people don't eat it, so in that case, מטמאין טומאת
אוכלין, mitam'in tum'at ochlin, it would be food. Who can eat hide?
Is it possible to cook hide enough that it's edible? Anyway, so
you see that even things that are not considered to be at
all be part food, if you make them edible, are food. So
therefore, everybody would agree even if you're going to call it wood,
once you fried it, it would be food.
אלא אמר רבא, Ella amar Rava,
so said Rava, let's just read this answer, איכא בינייהו ברכה. ika
beinaihu bracha. The difference would be ברכה, bracha, what type of ברכה
bracha you make on it. דאיתמר, it was stated, קור, kore, if
you have this heart of palm, רבי יהודה אומר בורא פרי האדמה
ושמואל אומר שהכל נהיה בדברו. Rabbi Yehuda omer borei pri ha'adama u'Shmuel
omer shehakol nihiya bidvaro. So what's that about? רבי יהודה אומר בורא
פרי האדמה אוכלא הוא, Rabbi Yehuda omer borei pri ha'adama ochla hu,
it is food. ושמואל אומר שהכל נהיה בדברו, V'Shmuel omer shehakol nihiya
bidvaro, that you make שהכל. shehakol. כיון שסופו להקשות, Kivan shesofo lehakshot,
because the heart of palm will turn into—and now we understand why
it's considered to be wood—not only is it part of the trunk,
but it will eventually turn into a trunk. So therefore, לא מברכינן
עליה בורא פרי האדמה. lo mivarchinan aleih borei pri ha'adama. You don't
say בורא פרי האדמה. borei pri ha'adama. אמר ליה שמואל לרב יהודה,
Amar lei Shmuel le-Rav Yehuda, so said Shmuel to Rav Yehuda, שיננא,
Shinina, sharp one, כוותיך מסתברא, kvatich mistabra, your opinion makes more sense
than mine. Why? דהא תנן, De-ha tnan, a radish, שסופו להקשות, shesofo
lehakshot, eventually gets hard, ומברכינן עליה בורא פרי האדמה, u'mivarchinan aleih borei
pri ha'adama, you still make בורא פרי האדמה borei pri ha'adama in
its current state. So the גמרא says, ולא היא, v'lo hi, but
you know what? That doesn't really prove רבי יהודה's position. תנן, Tnan,
a radish, ניטע אינש אדעתא דפוגלא, ni-ti inash a-da'ata d'pugla,
you plant it for the bulb, you plant it for the radish,
so the radish is obviously considered to be a fruit and you
make בורא פרי האדמה borei pri ha'adama or whatever, a vegetable. דיקלא,
Dikla, the palm tree, לא ניטע אינש אדעתא דקורא. lo ni-ti inash
a-da'ata d'kora. You don't plant a palm tree to get a heart
of palm. So therefore, I understand. So anyway, so the heart of
palm there could be considered it's part of the trunk, it'll be
hardened, maybe you don't make maybe you would always make a שהכל.
shehakol. So the one that says it's an עץ etz would say
it is so much categorically excluding you would always make you'd make
a שהכל, shehakol, and according to the תנא קמא, tanna kamma, although
they say it's not אוכל ochel for טומאת אוכלין purposes. They would
still say you make a בורא פרי האדמה *Borei Pri Haadama*. And
now we'll just end, ואף על גב דקלסיה שמואל לרב יהודה *ve-af
al gav de-kalsei Shmuel le-Rav Yehuda*, although שמואל *Shmuel* praised רב יהודה
*Rav Yehuda* and liked his opinion that it was בורא פרי האדמה
*Borei Pri Haadama*, הלכתא כוותיה דשמואל *hilchata kevasei de-Shmuel*, we rule like
שמואל *Shmuel* like we've been saying that it is more considered to
be wood and you would make a שהכל *Shehakol*.